"Is One Egg a Day Too Much?"
The NIH-AARP study,
sponsored by the National
Institutes of Health
and the American Association
of Retired Persons,
is the largest forward-looking,
in-depth study
on diet and health in history.
Based on its six million
person-years of observation,
replacing just three percent
of daily caloric intake
of animal protein
with plant protein
was associated
with a 10 percent decreased risk
of premature death.
Just a three percent swap!
Of all the animal
protein sources,
eggs were found
to be the worst.
Swapping in three percent
of plant protein for egg protein
was associated
with twice the benefit,
more than 20 percent
lower mortality,
having scrambled tofu instead.
In fact, each half an egg a day
was associated
with a seven percent increase
in all-cause mortality.
Just half an egg?
That's consistent with six
other U.S. cohort studies
that collectively found
that each additional
half an egg consumed per day
was significantly associated
with a higher risk
of getting
cardiovascular disease
and dying prematurely
from all causes put together.
And this higher risk of death
persisted
even after taking
other lifestyle behaviors
into account, including
overall dietary quality.
In other words,
it doesn't appear to just be
because people eating more eggs
were also eating more bacon,
for example.
A meta-analysis
of all such studies
confirmed that
greater egg consumption
confers higher risks of death
from all causes.
Another meta-analysis
including other types
of studies
involving nearly
12 million participants
echoed that it may be prudent
to avoid high egg consumption.
But what does "high" mean?
What's the safe amount?
It's not quite clear.
One meta-analysis suggests
there's little evidence
for elevated risks
below half an egg a day,
whereas another found
that adding
even one egg a week
to your diet
might increase your risk
of dying from cancer.
If the data on detriment
are so clear,
based on studies
involving millions of people,
why is there still controversy?
Because the egg industry
manufactures that controversy.
Just like the sugar industry
does with sugar.
Dr. Barnard's written about it.
I've written about it.
As noted by the director
of the Stroke Prevention
and Atherosclerosis
Research Centre,
"After being convicted
for false advertising
for suggesting
that eggs were safe,
the egg industry has spent
hundreds of millions of dollars
trying to convince the public,
physicians, and policy makers
that dietary cholesterol
and eggs are harmless."
Yet a meta-analysis
of more than 50
randomized controlled trials
found that egg consumption
significantly increases
LDL cholesterol.
Online, some bloggers parrot
the egg industry's
talking points
that the 2015 U.S.
dietary guidelines
removed the dietary
cholesterol limit
to consume
less than 300 milligrams
of dietary cholesterol a day,
whereas if anyone bothered
to actually read
the actual guidelines,
they'd see that the guidelines
actually strengthen
the recommendation
and tell Americans
to "eat as little dietary
cholesterol as possible,"
as recommended
by the Institute of Medicine,
the most prestigious
medical body
in the United States.
This advice was reiterated
in the most recent
dietary guidelines:
"The National Academies
recommends
that dietary
cholesterol consumption
be as low as possible,"
using the rationale
that any intake above zero
increases LDL cholesterol
concentration in the blood
and, therefore,
increases the risk
of the number one killer
of men and women.